Guide to the David M. Henderson Papers, 1964-1999 and undated RL.00529
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
David M. Henderson papers
1964-1999 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Henderson, David Martin
RL.00529
4.3 Linear Feet
David Martin Henderson graduated from Duke University in 1968. While based in Durham, North Carolina, he served as a newspaper editor and a long-time local, state-wide and national political activist. The David Martin Henderson Papers spans 1964-1989 and consists of correspondence and subject files containing letters, newspapers, clippings, pamphlets, broadsides, and internal organizational documents, all pertaining to Henderson's activities as a student radical at Duke University and a community organizer in Durham, N.C. Subjects covered by his papers include anti-war movements, Black Power, communism, G.I. rights, labor, Leninism, Marxism, women's liberation, Students for a Democratic Society and other affiliations.
Approximately 2,625 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The David M. Henderson Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift from 1972-2018.
Biographical Note
Originally from Texas, David Martin Henderson graduated from Duke University in 1968. As a political activist and newspaper editor, Henderson became involved in radical and activist organizations at Duke and in the city of Durham, NC; and was also active on a national scale in several organizations, political parties, and conferences.
Collection Overview
The David Martin Henderson Papers span the years 1964 to 1999, and contain organizational papers, correspondence, pamphlets, leaflets and broadsides concerning student organizations at Duke, UNC-Chapel Hill, and Harvard; personal correspondence between Henderson and family members (restricted); and printed material and correspondence concerning a number of other organizations, parties, and conferences, among them the North American Congress on Latin America (1967-1974), the Progressive Labor Party (1973-1976), and other organizations advocating communism and opposing U.S. foreign policy in Latin America and elsewhere. Much of the material was circulated by the Students for a Democratic Society (SDS) and its affiliates at Duke, the Student Liberation Front and its successor, Praxis. The collection concerns such topics as student governance and political action; race relations at Duke and in Durham; the Reserve Officers Training Corps; labor unions and city and campus workers; the movement to end the war in Vietnam; and socialist and communist organizations active at the time. Printed material includes items concerning the Southern Students Organizing Committee; two copies of the Socialist Worker, the newspaper of the North Carolina Socialist Union for which Henderson was an editor; typed and mimeographed papers of the North Carolina Socialist Union which was succeeded in Durham by the Progressive Workers Committee; the first issue of Proletarian Cause and draft articles for that publication. Authors including Tom Hayden and Stokeley Carmichael are represented in the papers along with several administrators of University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill.
Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Protest movements; Universities and colleges -- Employees; Student movements -- North Carolina; College students -- Political activity -- United States; United States -- Social conditions -- 1960-1980; United States -- Foreign relations -- Latin America; Durham (N.C.) -- Race relations; Progressive Labor Party; Radicals -- United States; Radicalism -- United States; Communism -- United States -- Societies, etc.; Labor unions -- United States -- History; Newspaper editors -- North Carolina; Political activists -- United States; Student movements -- Massachusetts; Socialism -- United States; Social Worker (N.C.); Carmichael, Stokely; Duke University -- Employees; Duke University -- Students -- Political activity; Harvard University -- Students -- Political activity; Hayden, Tom; Henderson, David Martin; North American Congress on Latin America; North Carolina Socialist Union; Southern Student Organizing Committee (Nashville, Tenn.); Students for a Democratic Society (U.S.); United States. Army. Reserve Officers' Training Corps; University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill -- Students -- Political activity
- Correspondence Series, 1964-1999 and undated (RESTRICTED), 3 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence Series consists of hand-written and typed correspondence of Henderson's mother, father, brother and other family members. Also consists of correspondence with friends, work colleagues and more. Related to the correspondence includes newspaper clippings and various other materials.
  Conditions Governing Access note
  RESTRICTED: Series is restricted; materials may only be used with donor's written permission.
  - Correspondence, 1964 Sept.-Oct. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1964 Nov.-Dec. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1965 Jan. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1965 Feb.-March (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1965 Apr.-May (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1965 Aug.-Oct. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1965 Nov.-Dec. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1966 Jan.-Sept. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1967 Apr.-Dec. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1968 Jan.-Dec. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1969 Mar.-Dec. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1970 Jan.-Dec. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1971 Jan.-Dec. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1972 Jan.-Dec. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1973 Jan.-Dec. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1974 Feb.-Dec. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1975 Jan.-Dec. (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1976 Jan.-Nov. (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1977 Jan.-Dec. (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1978 Mar. 1979-Dec. (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1980 Feb.-Nov. (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1981 Jan.-Dec. (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1982 Jan.-Aug. (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1982 Aug.-Dec. (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1983 Jan.-June (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1983 July-Dec. (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1984 Jan.-June. (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1984 July.-Dec. (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1985 Jan.-1986 Aug. (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1967-1999 (Box 9)
- Subject File Series, 1964-1989 and undated, 6 boxes
  Houses materials including ephemera, internal organizational materials, financial materials, school writings, and fugitive literature. Authors including Tom Hayden, Stokeley Carmichael, and University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill administrators such as J. Carlyle Sitterson and C.O. Cathey are represented as well.
  - Africa Research Group, 1969-1970 (Box 3)
    Includes one copy each of Radical Study Guide; International Dependency in the 1970's: How America underdevelops the world. A State of the Empire Report, and African Studies in America-The Extended Family: A Tribal Analysis of U.S. Africanists: Who They Are; Why to Fight Them.
  - Canadian Party of Labour, 1975-1976 (Box 3)
    Consists of one copy of The Canadian Party of Labour Handbook and The "Scientific" Killers and Who Sent for Them: A Communist Response to Theories of "Overpopulation." Also includes program and list of workshops for the International Communist Conference of Workers held in Detroit, Michigan from January 24-25, 1976.
  - Clippings, 1976 (Box 3)
    Consists of one Letter to the Editor written by Henderson published February 11, 1976 in an unidentified newspaper.
  - Committee Against Racism, 1975-1976 (Box 3)
    Includes one copy of INCAR and the Struggle Against Racism, a report entitled Report of the CAR Work: A Critical Evaluation, and a stock letter regarding regional organization meetings.
  - Communist Conference, 1975-1976 (Box 3)
    Houses bi-monthly bulletins numbered 1, 2, 3, 6, and 8 published by the Communist Conference, originally called the Trade Union Conference.
  - Communist League, 1969-1972 Aug. (Box 3)
    Consists of one copy each of Communist League New Member Outline; Labor Reports: Draft, 1971; volume 2, number 2 of Proletariat: A Theoretical Journal Published by the Communist League. Also houses two copies of the People's Tribune from April and August, 1972, and a collection of documents adopted by the second congress of the Communist League in January 1969.
  - Communist League, 1972 Sept.-Dec. (Box 3)
    Includes one copy of Negro National Colonial Question in addition to volume 2, number 1 of Proletariat: A Theoretical Journal Published by the Communist League. Also contains the September 1972 edition of the People's Tribune; a Western Union mailgram requesting contact; and a document entitled, Call for a Conference of North American Marxist Leninists Issued by the Preparatory Committee for the Conference-November 19, 1972.
  - Durham, N.C., 1970 (Box 3)
    Includes one flyer, newspaper clippings, letter from the City-wide Strike Support Committee, and related materials.
  - Durham County Hospital, undated (Box 3)
    Consists of one flyer produced by the North Carolina Socialist Union calling on citizens to resist the plan to construct a new Durham County Hospital.
  - Duke University, 1969 Feb.-Oct. (Box 3)
    Houses newspaper clippings and one full newspaper dated from May 13, 1969 of The Duke Chronicle. Contains an SDS meeting agenda; one sermon by Rev. Dr. Howard C. Wilkinson entitled Plain Talk About Our University; Duke Student Union materials; one open letter to the R.O.T.C. from the Student Liberation Front; one hand-written letter to the Central Committee; and four flyers related to Local Union 1199/RWDSU/AFL-CIO, National Organizing Committee of Hospital and Nursing Home Employees.
  - Duke University, undated (Box 3)
    Consists of flyers related to R.O.T.C and anti-war; SDS flyers related to women workers, non-academic workers, racism, and CIA Recruiters; Local Union 1199 flyer related to Johns Hopkins Workers; newspaper clippings; an open letter regarding non-academic employees; one essay related to the Free University Departmental Unions; and one hand-written note.
  - Duke University, undated (Box 3)
    Includes flyers related to race relations, neighborhood relations, the vigil, Knightwatch, and workers and unions. Also contains one draft article; one essay related to Student Government; one SLAM meeting flyer; and one pamphlet entitled The Blacks Have Left Duke. Where Do You Stand?
  - Education, 1972 and undated (Box 3)
    Contains two copies of the Freedom Press, one dated September 1972 and the other October 1972. Also includes two essays entitled University Analysis and The Faculty--Our Ally or Theirs?
  - Financial Records, 1969 and undated (Box 3)
    Consists of various records and statements from student groups, individuals and The Duke Chronicle.
  - Georgia Communist League, 1967-1972 and undated (Box 3)
    Includes a pamphlet entitled On the Questions of Stalin: Reference Material for the Study of 'A Great Historical Document'; a Workers' Books catalog from 1972; a receipt of books purchased from Workers' Books by Henderson in 1971; two issues of Spark dated July 2, 1971 and October 10, 1971; an internal edition of the Spark and two copies of The Vanguard Party: The Invincible Weapon of the Working Class. Also includes a collection of undated essays with the following titles: The Urgent Tasks of our Movement, The Fight for a New Party and our Political Tasks, Armed Struggle vs. Peaceful Transition to Socialism, Revolution at the Role of SCEF, and Call for a Conference to Establish a Southern Editorial Board for the Marxist-Leninist Journal.
  - G.I. Rights, 1968-1969 (Box 3)
    Houses one pamphlet entitled Two GIs in the Struggle published by SDS; copies of speeches and press statements compiled by American Deserters Committee; newspaper clippings; materials from Resistance, Fort Hood Three Defense Committee, United Anti-War Mobilization Front (UAWMF), Southern Student Organizing Committee (SSOC), Veterans for Peace in Vietnam, GIs United Against The War in Vietnam, The Young Socialist Alliance in Chapel Hill and Durham, and the GI-Civilian Mobilization for Peace. Also contains newsletter Mobilizer: To Get U.S. Out of Vietnam; and correspondence from U.S. Department of the Army and one pamphlet entitled Judgment at Fort Jackson: The Trial of Howard Levy M.D. reprinted from Christianity and Crisis.
  - Harvard University, 1969-1970 (Box 3)
    Includes statements from the Harvard-Radcliffe SDS, Harvard Progressive Labor Party, The Cambridge Peace and Freedom Party, and one statement related to the Committee of Fifteen. Also contains pamphlet entitled Harvard, Urban Imperialist produced by the Anti-expansion Anti-R.O.T.C Strike Steering Committee.
  - Harvard University, 1969-1970 (Box 3)
    Consists of statements by Harvard-Radcliffe SDS and the Anti-expansion Anti-R.O.T.C Strike Steering Committee. Also includes newspaper clipping and one pamphlet entitled Free Speech at Harvard: An Answer to Various Deans produced by the Progressive Labor Party.
  - Helsinki International Student Week, 1967 (Box 3)
    One bound volume entitled The 6th Helsinki International Student Week, September 21-October 1, 1967.
  - Journal Correspondence, 1972 (Box 3)
    Consists of a collection of letters to and from Henderson regarding various publications and meetings of the Communist League.
  - Labor, 1967-1970 (Box 4)
    Contains worker contract. Also contains one pamphlet entitled Corporate Profits and the Wage Gap reprinted from AFL-CIO American Federationist. Includes newspaper clipping from The Washington Post; letters from AfSCME, AFL-CIO and City-wide Strike Support Committee; flyers pertaining to workers in Greensboro, NC and boycotts for Valleydale Meat Products; statements from UNC-Duke SDS; and one 16-page student essay titled The Engineer.
  - Labor, 1967-1970 (Box 4)
    Houses one 16-page essay titled The Resort Hotel Bellman: Report of a Participant Observer. Contains statements from SDS at Austin, Brandeis, Columbia-Barnard, Harvard-Radcliffe, MIT, New School, NYU, UCLA, Yale, and Bay Area Spartacist League Chapters. Also contains statement from Student Labor Action Project (SLAP); flyers related to G.E. workers distributed by Praxis; and one copy of City Employees Newsletter Local 1194.
  - Labor, 1967-1970 and undated (Box 4)
    Includes pamphlets entitled On Strike: State Senate Scabs on Boston Strikers! and Two Ways to Fight-For the Bosses...Or Against Them! both produced by Cambridge Peace and Freedom Party. Contains SDS materials related to G.E. Workers and Vietnam; materials from AFL-CIO and Local Union 1199 Chapter at Mount Sinai Medical Center; a first edition of The Red Metalworker; and newspaper clipping from The Durham Morning Herald.
  - Labor, 1970-1976 (Box 4)
    Consists of one copy of Grow: A New Movement in the White South, which includes information on the activities of Bob Zellner, in addition to several copies of Meatcutters' Rank-and-File News, The G.E. Organizer, and Gold Kist Rank-and-File News. Several fliers relate to organizing Local 465. There is one paper entitled Ad Hoc Caucus Against Class Collaboration: Short Statement on Principle and Program. Also includes one copy of UE Southern Voice: Newspaper of the UE Southern Conference and a February 23, 1971 Duke Chronicle article entitled Bringing the student-working alliance home.
  - Labor, 1199 Drug and Hospital News, 1969 (Box 4)
    Contains three issues from May-July 1969.
  - Legal, 1972 (Box 4)
    Includes one letter from the Durham Police Department returning $1 to Henderson.
  - Miscellaneous, 1966-1970 (Box 4)
    Consists of pamphlet entitled Power and Racism by Stokeley Carmichael; one newsletter from Rent Control Referendum entitled Stay and Fight; one catalog from China Publications; one newsletter entitled Dateline=Ithaca. Also includes a Graduate Student Directory List; letters; one illustration; one flyer; one Community VISTA volunteer application; and one newspaper clipping from The Baltimore Sun.
  - Miscellaneous, 1967-1975 and undated (Box 4)
    Includes White Blindspot by J. H. Kagin; two copies of White Blindspot and Can White Radicals be Radicalized? by Noel Ignatin; one copy of The Tupamaros: Urban Guerrilla Warfare in Uruguay; numbers 4 and 5 of Tricontinental: North American Edition; one issue of the Louisville Red Banner and an order form for the Peoples Press. Also includes two essays: Can American Workers Make a Socialist Revolution? and Biblical Reflections on Viet Nam. There is a copy of City of Durham Housing Standards and three fliers selling poetry and photographs from Cuba, Vietnam, and Latin America.
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 4)
    Contains flyers related to G.E. strikers; pamphlet from Young Socialist Alliance; booklists; conference materials; statement from social and student groups; newspaper clippings from The Durham Morning Herald; and literature entitled Revolutionary Youth Movement published by Radical Education Project.
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 4)
    Consists of three birthday cards to Henderson.
  - New England Free Press, undated (Box 4)
    Houses two different pamphlets entitled Radical Literature for the Movement from the New England Free Press.
  - North American Congress on Latin America, 1967-1968 (Box 4)
    Volume I, issues 1-10 and volume II, issues 1-8 of the North American Congress on Latin America (NACLA) Newsletter.
  - North American Congress on Latin America, 1969-1970 Apr. (Box 4)
    Volume II, issues 9-10; volume III, issues 1-10 and volume IV, issues 1-2 of NACLA Newsletter. Also includes one copy of The Hanna Industrial Complex.
  - North American Congress on Latin America, 1970 May-Dec. (Box 4)
    Volume IV, issues 3-8 of NACLA Newsletter. Folder also consists of one copy each of Subliminal Warfare: The Role of Latin American Studies and The University-Military-Police Complex: A Directory and Related Documents.
  - North American Congress on Latin America, 1971 (Box 4)
    Volume IV, issues 9-10; volume V, issues 1, 3-8 of NACLA Newsletter. The newsletter changes its name to NACLA'S Latin American and Empire Report with volume V, issue 7.
  - North American Congress on Latin America, 1972 (Box 5)
    Volume VI, issues 1-10 of NACLA'S Latin American and Empire Report.
  - North American Congress on Latin America, 1973 (Box 5)
    Volume VII, issues 1, 4-10 of NACLA'S Latin American and Empire Report.
  - North American Congress on Latin America, 1974 (Box 5)
    Volume VIII, issues 1-4 and 6-10 of NACLA'S Latin American and Empire Report.
  - North Carolina Socialist Union, 1972 Jan.-June (Box 5)
    Includes financial statements, various flyers, hand-written and typed letters, and internal documents regarding the organization.
  - North Carolina Socialist Union, 1972 July-Aug. (Box 5)
    Consists of one copy of the Socialist Worker; agendas and minutes from meetings; and hand-written notes.
  - North Carolina Socialist Union, 1972 Sept.-Nov. (Box 5)
    Contains two copies of the Socialist Worker; and agendas, minutes, reports and resolutions from meetings. Also includes one essay and hand-written meeting notes.
  - North Carolina Socialist Union, undated (Box 5)
    Includes organizational materials; magazine clippings; open letters; hand-written letters; and various flyers. Also contains four pamphlets entitled Mississippi vs. North Carolina: Lowest Wages, Overtime-Who Benefits?, Taxes-Who Pays?, and Workers are Dying Trying to Earn a Living.
  - North Carolina Socialist Union, 1972 Sept.-Oct.,"Socialist Worker" (Box 5)
    Houses Socialist Worker from September and October 1972.
  - Occupational Safety and Health, 1972-1974 and undated (Box 5)
    Includes one copy of Health Hazards in the Workplace; two copies of a Health/PAC Bulletin; a Washington Post special on hospitals; number 4 of the Occupational Health Project Report; one issue of Mountain Life and Work; an occupational safety pamphlet put together by Durham Area Conference on Occupational Health and Safety; correspondence and fliers regarding Burlington, North Carolina service workers, and a collection of handwritten notes and business cards. Also a collection of registration cards from a 1963 Occupational Safety conference.
  - October League, 1971-1972 (Box 5)
    Consists of ten copies of The Red Worker from 1971-1972; the first issue of The Call, one copy of Women Hold Up Half the Sky; several copies of The Red Metalworker. Also one copy of Have You Heard?: ELA Community Newsletter and three newsletters from October League (one is titled Ignition!, though the group latter changed the name to Blowout!). There are also two internal documents from the group: Proposal for Consolidation of Unity with the October League and Draft of the Political Statement of Unity.
  - The Philadelphia Free Press, 1972 (Box 6)
    Consists of oversized material including one copy The Philadelphia Free Press newspaper dated November 1972. Also includes one pamphlet entitled The Spirit of George Jackson: The Life of George Jackson and the Truth About Prisons and Prisoners in America. Contains one subscription letter.
  - Praxis, 1969-1970 and undated (Box 6)
    Consists of financial records, various flyers related to Vietnam, internal documents and essays related to Socialism.
  - Progressive Labor Party, 1973 Jan.-Apr. (Box 6)
    Houses six Progressive Labor Party Convention Bulletins numbering 1-6.
  - Progressive Labor Party, 1973 May-June (Box 6)
    Houses five Progressive Labor Party Convention Bulletins numbering 7-11.
  - Progressive Labor Party, 1973 July (Box 6)
    Houses three Progressive Labor Party Convention Bulletins numbering 12A-12C. Contains Convention Reports. Also includes administrative and records reports.
  - Progressive Labor Party, 1973 Aug.-Sept. (Box 6)
    Contains oversized materials including four-page newspaper titled Special PLP Bulletin on the Current Class Struggle in Auto; and Internal Bulletin number 2.
  - Progressive Labor Party, 1974 (Box 6)
    Includes four Progressive Labor Party Internal Bulletins; one copy of Challenge: The Revolutionary Communist Newspaper; two letters; and one report on unemployment.
  - Progressive Labor Party, 1975 (Box 6)
    Consists of three reports including two reports from National Committee Meetings, and an Internal Bulletin dated November 3; three pamphlets entitled March on May Day: The Fight for the Shorter Work-Day, Thunder in the Mines: The Miller UMW Machine-Blue-print for Fascism, and Win With Marxism-Leninism (Triunfemos con el Marxismo-Leninismo); and several other bulletins.
  - Progressive Labor Party, 1976 Jan.-Aug. (Box 6)
    Includes several newsletters including Tobacco Workers Caucus Fight Back!, Challenge,The G.E. Spark!, On the Line, and The Duke Workers Solidarity. Also contains newspaper clippings; an essay related to tobacco workers; a letter from the May Day Committee; and a 1976 issue of National Committee Report.
  - Progressive Labor Party, 1976 (Box 6)
    Houses one pamphlet entitled A Connecticut Communist in a Kangaroo Court: Fighting Fascism in the Public Schools. Also includes one newsletter from North Carolina Hard Times Prison Project.
  - Progressive Labor Party, undated (Box 6)
    Contains two National Committee Reports from May 25-26 and Aug.1-3 Meetings; one Bulletin entitled Second Progress Report From Minnesota NPW; letters; one Special Edition copy of Challenge; and a draft cover of Challenge.